Guide to the Leonard Greenburg Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leonard C. Greenburg papers
1911-1946
MS 1320
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
Research studies, notes, writings, correspondence, photographs and printed matter chiefly connected with Greenberg's position as sanitary engineer in the United States Public Health Service (1918-1932). Most of the papers concern hazards to the health of industrial workers, but also materials on several research projects including a study of Bacillus acidophilus and a project conducted in collaboration with C.-E.A. Winslow on skin temperature. The correspondence is largely professional, with only a few family letters and a small number from his teachers at Yale, C-E.A. Winslow and Ira V. Hiscock. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection in the Yale University Library.
Greenburg, Leonard, 1892-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Yale University Dept. of Epidemiology and Public Health.
Biographical / Historical
LEONARD GREENBURG, 1892--
1892 - born in New York City
1915 - received C.E. From Columbia University School of Engineering
1918-1932 - worked for United States Public Health Service
1923 - received Ph. D. from Yale University
1923-1950 - Lecturer, Clinical Professor of Public Health, Yale University
1930 - received MD from Yale University
1935-1952 - Director, Industrial Hygiene, New York State Dept. of Labor
1949 - received Certification in Public Health
1951 - Associate Clinical Professor, New York University -- Bellevue Hospital
1952-1960 - Commissioner, Air Pollution Control, City of New York
1956 - received Certification in Occupational Medicine
1960-1966 - Professor, Chairman, Dept. of Preventive and Environmental Medicine, Albert Einstein College of Medicine
1967- - Professor Emeritus, Dept. of Preventive Medicine and Community Health, Albert Einstein College of Medicine
-- from the Directory of Medical Specialists, 20th ed., 1981-82, p. 2869 (Preventive Medicine); Historical Register of Yale University, 1937-51, p. 165.
Scope and Contents
The Leonard Greenburg Papers primarily date from the early part of Greenburg's career, 1918-1932, when he was sanitary engineer in the United States Public Health Service. Most of his work concerned hazards to the health of industrial workers, such as accidents and toxic substances; the subject files, which constitute the bulk of the collection, document several of his on-site studies and investigations. Also in these files are materials regarding Greenburg's involvement in the manufacture of a milk product, Bacillus acidophilus, and papers concerning a research project, on which he collaborated with C.-E. A. Winslow, on the changes in skin temperature produced by drafts of air.
The subject files contain correspondence, notes, drafts, writings, legal and financial papers, printed matter, and photographs. They are followed by seven folders of miscellaneous "personal papers" -- correspondence, legal papers, and notes, arranged chronologically -- and two folders of miscellaneous photographs and printed matter. Most of the correspondence in the collection is from co-workers or plant representatives, with only a small amount of family correspondence and only one or two letters from Greenburg's teachers and colleagues at Yale, C.-E. A. Winslow and Ira V. Hiscock.
Details of Greenburg's various appointments in the USPHS, and a summary of his education and work experience to 1931, may be found in a letter of 1931 Sep 18 and its enclosures (in folder 10). Another folder contains a list of his early publications.
The papers were accessioned from the Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, ca. 1971.
General
Forms part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Industrial hygiene; Milk -- Microbiology; Public health; Health-officers; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Greenburg, Leonard, 1892-1991; Hiscock, Ira V. (Ira Vaughan), 1892-; Winslow, C.-E. A. (Charles-Edward Amory), 1877-1957; United States. Public Health Service
- Inventory
  - Subject files
    - Accidents, 1921-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Asbestos (Multibestos Company, Walpole, Mass.), 1929-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Bacillus acidophilus, 1920-1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 4 - 8)
      General note
      See also: Inventory Folder 31
    - Benzol poisoning (Ida S. Pelton case), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Castor bean dust (Berkshire Chemical Co., Bridgeport, Conn.)
      - Correspondence, 1928-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 10 - 11)
      - Report: rough draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Report: final drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Notes, drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Lead poisoning (Balbach Plant, Newark, N.J.), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Oils (U.S. Rubber Regenerating Co., Naugatuck, Conn.), 1929-1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Skin temperature study
      - Paper, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Paper: draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Financial and legal papers, 1928-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Miscellaneous papers, 1921, 1928-1930, undated (Box 2, Folder 20 - 22)
  - Personal papers, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 23 - 24)
  - Personal papers, 1930-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 25 - 29)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1911, 1913, 1920-1928, 1939, 1946, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)